27 chapter 28 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 28 A Job Horse and His
Drivers hither to I had always been driven by people who at least knew how
to drive; but in this place I was to get my experience of all the different kinds
of bad and ignorant driving to which we horses are subjected; for I was a “job
horse”, and was let out to all sorts of people who wished to hire me; and as I
was good-tempered and gentle, I think I was often a let out to the ignorant
drivers than some of the other horses, because I could be depended upon. It
would take a long time to tell of all the different styles in which I was
driven, but I will mention a few of them. First, there were the tight rain
drivers— —men who seemed to think that all depended on holding the rains as hard as
they could, never relaxing the pull on the horse's mouth, or giving him the
least liberty of movement. They always talking about “keeping the horse well in
hand”, and “holding a horse up”, just as if a horse was not made to hold himself up.
Some poor broken down horses, whose mouths have been made hard and
insensible by just such drivers as these, may, perhaps, find some support in it; but
for a horse who can depend on his own legs, and who has a tender mouth and is
easily guided, it is not only tormenting, but it is stupid. Then there are the loose rain
drivers, who let the rains lie easily on our backs, and their own hand rest lazily
on their knees. Of course, such gentlemen have no control over a horse, if anything happens
suddenly. If a horse shies, or starts, or stumbles, they are nowhere, and cannot
help the horse or the elves till the mischief is done. Of course, for myself I
had no objection to it, as I was not in the habit of either starting or
stumbling, and had only been used to depend on my driver for guidance and
encouragement. Still, one likes to feel the rain a little in going downhill, and
likes to know that one's driver is not gone to sleep. Besides, a slovenly way of driving
gets a horse into bad and often lazy habits, and when he changes hands he has
to be whipped out of them with more or less pain and TR trouble. Squire Gordon
always kept us to our best paces and our best manners. He said that spoiling a
horse and letting him get into bad habits was just as cruel as spoiling a
child, and both had to suffer for it afterward. Besides, these drivers are
often careless altogether, and will attend to anything else more than their
horses. I went out in the fighton one day
with one of them; he had a lady and two children behind. He flopped the rains
about as we started, and of course gave me several unmeaning cuts with a whip,
though I was fairly off. There had been a good deal of Road
mending going on, and even where the stones were not freshly laid down there
were a great many loose ones about. My driver was laughing and joking with the
lady and the children, and talking about the country to the right and the left;
but he never thought it worthwhile to keep an eye on his horse or to drive on
the smoothest parts of the road; and so it easily happened that I got a stone
into one of my for feet. Now, if Mr. Gordon or John, or in fact
any good driver, had been there, he would have seen that something was wrong
before I had gone three paces. Or even if it had been dark a practiced hand would
have felt by the rain that there was something wrong in the step, and they
would have got down and picked out the stone. But this man went on laughing and
talking, while at every step the stone became more firmly wedged between my
shoe and the frog of my foot. The stone was sharp on the inside
and round on the outside, which, as everyone knows, is the most dangerous
kind that a horse can pick up, at the same time cutting his foot and making
him most liable to stumble and fall. Whether the man was partly blind or
only very careless I can't say, but he drove me with that stone in my foot for
a good half mile before he saw anything. By that time I was going so
lame with the pain that at last he saw it, and called out, “Well, here's ago Why,
they have sent us out with a lame horse!
What a shame!” He then chucked the rains and flipped about with the whip, saying, “Now,
then, it's no use playing the old soldier with me; there's the journey to go, and
it's no use turning lame and lazy.” Just at this time a farmer came
riding up on a brown cob. He lifted his hat and pulled up. “I beg your pardon, sir,”
he said, “but I think there is something the matter with your horse; he goes very
much as if he had a stone in his shoe. If
you will allow me I will look at his feet; these loose scattered stones are
confounded dangerous things for the horses.” “He's a hired horse,” said my driver.
“I don't know what's the matter with him, but it is a great shame to send out a
lame beast like this.” The farmer dismounted, and slipping
his rain over his arm at once took up my near
foot. “Bless me, there's a stone! Lame! I should think
so!” At first he tried to dislodge it with his hand, but as it was now very tightly
wedged he drew a stone pick out of his pocket, and very carefully and with some
trouble got it out. Then holding it up he said, “There, that's the stone your horse had picked
up. It is a wonder he did not fall down and break his knees into the
bargain!” “Well, to be sure!” said my driver; “that is a queer thing! I never knew that
horses picked up stones before.” “Didn't you?” said the farmer rather
contemptuously; “but they do, though, and the best of them will do it, and can't
help it sometimes on such roads as these.
And if you don't want to lame your horse you must look sharp and get them out
quickly. This foot is very much bruised,” he said, setting it down gently and
patting me. “If I might advise, sir, you had better drive him gently for a while the
foot is a good deal hurt, and the lameness will not go off
directly.” Then mounting his cob and raising his hat to the lady he trotted
off. When he was gone my driver began to Flo the rains about and whip the harness,
by which I understood that I was to go on, which of course I did, glad that the
stone was gone, but still in a great deal of pain. This was the sort of experience we
job horses often came in for end of chapter